so welcome everyone I'm joined with mark
Vernon today he's the author of many
books he's had some podcast series he's
done some a couple of videos interesting
commentary on my work on awakening from
the meeting crisis and so I'll let mark
introduce himself more so welcome mark
thanks very much John it's nice to speak
to you having you know what's the little
we're doing from afar I particularly sat
up though when you started talking about
Owen Barfield in a couple of talks cuz
he's a chap that has been very
inspirational to me
I mean he's what he's done is he brought
a lot of things together for me or at
least I guess found he helped me find a
way to bring together a lot of things
which you know it's not unrelated to the
whole issue of the meaning of crisis and
I used to be a church England clergy
person for one thing and then sort of
fell out of love with that left
I did a philosophy PhD on Plato spend
the whole time thinking that I wasn't
quite getting to grits law Plato was
saying even though I got the PhD
apparently fine I've even got a past in
physics my undergraduate degree was in
physics and and quite you know how that
fits into things again so he helped me
sort of bring together a lot of things
primarily actually by this notion he had
of kind of unthinking what you think you
know mmm-hmm and seeing what pops up and
when you can do that and so you know
that starts to make more sense of
Socrates it starts to make more sense of
the crisis which we face now
particularly within Christianity but I
think he's really presented as too
rational really you know as if X for as
wise fall is dead even in relatively
liberal traditions like my own so he
began to create kind of imaginative
space and the course imagination is a
big big thing football fields so he
helped me to do yeah so there's a few
things I'd like to pick up on that
well actually three but the first two
that came to mind was you you reference
the particular relationship you think
this pairs to Christianity and this this
brings up your recent book mark has a
book out it's very well written by the
way
in fact I I find I I mean a lot of
convergent agreement with the book and a
lot of powerful ways but it's also very
beautifully written it's called the
secret history of Christianity is that
correct
thanks and that I do recommend it I
think it's a very good read as you know
many many of you know I'm in dialogue
with many people like Paul bender clay
and Jonathan pazzo Mary Cohen JP Marceau
Christians and who are very attracted
and interested in a very good faith way
in my work and I am interested in what
they're doing
I'm having this interesting dialogue
with Christianity so the mention both
points mark and then you can play with
them as you wish and the first is you
know what like you know you know there's
sort of there's sort of you know
critical of Christianity in fact at the
very beginning in the book I think the
first sentence is something like there's
something wrong with Christianity today
you start very critically so there is
something wrong and then there's maybe a
difference of opinion or maybe view
ultimately about whether or not this is
sickness unto death or whether or not
it's a you know portends a potential
reformulation or revival so what's the
relationship to Christianity that you
see Barfield and then how does that
relate to you know the Nietzschean death
of God but also the more broadly the
meaning crisis so I'm giving you this
very loosely formulated question because
I want to give you a lot of room to play
in and then the other notion that came
to mind is and these two terms because I
think and when you win when you're
talking about logos in your book and I
believe because of Socrates the Athenian
Moses or the Moses of Athens and Barr
fields critical of the notion of
rationality I'm very critical of what I
call the Enlightenment know
of rationality and I've tried to give a
notion that's much more Socratic is the
adjective and then because that the
modern notion of rationality and here's
what I'm going to get to the term you
brought up but I want these two talked
about together if possible please is
imagination because you're also using
imagination in a way that's different
how it's commonly used or commonly
understood so the person that's been
most helpful for me on that
apart from Barfield and Lachman
lachman's book was a very good book ah
lost knowledge of the imagination I
believe it is what it's called is
especially the work of Corbin and and
the commentary and excellent work and I
had a discussion with Thomas chief
enough about this the notion of the
distinction between the imaginal and the
merely imaginary so could you talk a
little I know I'm giving you a lot here
but I want to give you a lot of space to
play with so Christianity the meaning
crisis Barfield right and then you know
playing off against each other I think I
think they require sort of a reciprocal
reformulation imagination and
rationality or reason I had a really
excellent conversation about with Ian
McGilchrist about this to the master
news emissary so there's a lot there
I've tried to feed you a lot so now well
yeah
pick up in a couple of threads and see
where they go yeah I mean maybe start
where you ended up there and think
because because Coleridge is another big
name for yes yes yes yeah and encoder
which is idea was that you can tell the
difference between the imagination and
say mere fantasy which is to think a bit
like core bands difference between the
imaginal and regular kind of imagination
because the imaginable or imagination
with the capital i' encoder rich it
takes you somewhere it's not just sort
of fun although it might be fun it's not
just playing on what you already know
although it would do that but actually
extends and develops and carries you
into new perceptions of reality new
knowledge new awareness and I think that
the reason reasons tasks is a sense
discerning what the imagination throws
up again it's not its reason meant in
the sense of incorporating beauty and
pattern yes and again this sort of the
reach of experience and reality that
reason enables you to kind of relate to
more precisely rather than just is it
coherent illogical arabia's pretty good
actually yeah so and then there's then
the sort of theistic element which I
have found a persuasive having kind of
gone through I can meet you in death of
God and try to find a way back which is
that this must be a sharing I think with
a broader sense of insight these bar
fills expression the inside of the whole
world it's not something just going on
inside our own heads because otherwise
it wouldn't really go anywhere it would
just turn around in epicycles and sort
of consume itself and sometimes feel a
bit exhausted sometimes a bit exciting
but not really with a sense of life
further inspired seeing as much as kind
of enables you to to co-create with it
and so the code originally an idea that
our imagination with the capital I and I
think this is in core band to the
imaginal as actually taking us to Ward's
spirit not just amplifying our own inner
life and that took me back in the
direction of a theistic conception of
things so that's to say something about
that sort of sighs I mean yeah the
Christian bit particularly my criticism
and this is very much my own story as
you know when I first started getting
involved in the church as an adult there
was a big move around while
demythologizing in one way to turn
Christianity into sort of symbols for a
moral life mm-hmm and I feel very
passionately against that now because I
think morality sets up laws and rules
and so it doesn't enable you to be free
really and it's all about what you're
you know managing to sort of Richie
Eve in your life rather than is your
life really expanding and growing it
judges but judges not so as to release
you to something bigger but just purely
to sort of keep you in place so that was
one side of Christianity that liberal
Christianity I knew the other side was
and the non realism of figures like Dom
Cupid and who's still just about writing
I think and but he sort of felt that you
know religious rituals are good for
their own sake they kind of take you
outside yourself a bit and they enable
you to connect with place and history
and that side of things they probably
have some psychological benefit and I
mean I can see that but again it felt
like at the end of the day you know
you've got to kind of keep your own will
assets you know you've got to kind of
stir up the energy from within rather
than energy coming from without it felt
like a closed system rather than an open
system and Barfield helped me with that
because what he tells is also a story of
Christianity and why we've come to this
particular moment with Christianity you
know whether or not Christianity will
provide oh no it remains to be seen I
think it could be that the the big
Christian cycle you know that reached
its culmination in the medieval period
is the Christian cycle and something
else emerges now I'm kind of open to
that possibility
nonetheless he felt that what it did was
it released a new way that we experience
ourselves as human beings and
particularly as individuals and by that
he meant that we have a rich kind of
inner life that we can claim to some
substantial extent is our own that we
have real choices over it and that we
can therefore find a path for
development through life and know that
their inner life mirrors and the inner
life ultimately of the divine you know
the divine I am this in the monotheistic
conception can be seen by the individual
that has a gathered sense of themselves
if not can say I am themselves
and that was tremendously energizing for
the Christian period around the
Mediterranean particularly and it led to
the great flourishing of medieval
Christianity but went through a phase of
alienation in the early modern period
and for Barfield alienation isn't always
isn't just bad it's both good and bad
it's got the bat outside which is the
common the understood side that it
creates the meaning crisis but he also
thought that it throws you on yourself
and if you can use the opportunity if
you can sort of survive the struggle
actually deepens your own inner life
with the potential then that opens back
onto the inner life of all things with a
with a renewed consciousness and you
renewed deliberation to do it but also
renewed perceptions and so that that's
the question mark in a way that hangs
over our own time I think he thought
that it happened with the birth of Greek
philosophy and also the Hebrew prophets
radical revolution I'm Holdings going on
back then it sort of found its
culmination around the figure of Jesus
particularly for those who turn to
Christianity became hugely productive
fruitful and so on but you know again
there's a kind of cycle now where all
this has kind of thrown into question
with the good and the bad the fact
produces that was really good
no it's very good I enjoyed that very
much so there was a couple of
interesting things so you gave you used
a very very important term for me when
you described reasons first of all you
know the imagination as the education in
the deep sense of to draw forth right
and like is it a perception which which
are by the way is finding a lot of
consonants within current cognitive
science the relationship between imagine
imagination perception is much more like
that than what we used to think so I
think that's an important point you
might want to come back to but you said
that reason has they're full of
discernment which is something that I
like because discernment of course is
all
so a term about understanding and wisdom
it has the idea of seeing through what's
a losery into what's real and you're
bringing in that you know that we should
what well this is what I argue I think
that we should move rationality off it's
fake fixation on sort of logical
coherence to produce certain conclusions
and I'm doing certain like this instead
we should make it back to what we see in
Socrates and Plato which is as you say
the training of discernment the ability
to see through self-deception to see
through illusory aspects the way in
which things present themselves is not
always the way they are the way we
understand ourselves can be
fundamentally misleading or biased in
all kinds away and so I think that's
very consonant I think that's very
consonant but when you were talking
about Christ and Christianity and they
can sort of the gathering together the
Kairos around him one of the things that
I didn't wanted to ask you is given
let's let's sort of a matter we'll put
together you know in imagination and
reason as discernment as sort of a
unified faculty and right and we'll just
we won't name it but we'll say that
there is this faculty is that okay or
are you okay with them and then what I
want to know is you'll see why what this
what this has to do with you know
participation and especially post axial
reciprocal what you call reciprocal
participation following Barfield as you
know I think I quite independently came
to the notion of participatory knowing
through 14 Karzai and I and there's deep
and that's how I asked how I came to
Barfield I came to Barfield through I
was searching about anybody who had been
talking about this and of course I was
thrown into Plato and people but then I
get Barfield came up that's how I came
to Barfield actually through that and so
I want to talk about the relationship
between this reason imagination
imagination reason faculty and
participation participatory knowing and
reciprocal participation in particular
because I think reciprocal participation
is seeing an important revival in these
two notions of reciprocal narrowing in
things
addiction which should be thought of as
existential and not merely psychological
their psychological of course but
they're not merely psychological their
existential as well right and the
opposite reciprocal opening which right
has a lot to do with meaning in life and
I like your point also and then I'll
stop talking so you can talk some more
that and trying to reduce religion to
morality which is still a strong impulse
today I think is deeply mistaken because
I think that sense of connectedness
religio which i think has an important
role within reciprocal participation has
a lot more to do with meaning in life
and meaning in life is about this
fundamental sense of connectedness and
it's and it's neither the passive
reception of empiricism nor the active
projection of at least four so Ian's
romanticism you and I differ differ a
little bit about how but I think you
agree with me that Rousseau at least has
this you know this is the this notion of
Romanticism that's very much about sort
of expressing right and painting on the
empty canvas of the world and and so the
notion of connectedness that people are
seeking in meaning in life is neither
that path that purely passive or that
purely aggressive one and and and and
and in his book on Owen Barfield Aoife
zuzia actually brings this out as a
really important point about Barr fields
notion of participation so there again
I've tried to give you a bunch because
the last time I gave you a lot with it
so go again work that was good luck yeah
thank you yeah I mean I think what you
say and those distinctions are right and
I've never liked the roost own kind of
Romanticism I mean Barfield actually he
felt the romanticism needs to come of
age as he put it and I think part of
that is his criticism of Rousseau but
also the tendency in say words worth
just to kind of fall back on wonder or
mystery yeah I'm and to enjoy the
sentiment but not really be able to make
much more obvious yeah although
Wordsworth is a genius but yes though I
mean actually just to throw in another
little bit of my own bio biography
because this in a way it's a keep
practice for me and I know the Kratz is
becoming more important for you as well
I work as a psychotherapist my kind of
everyday certainly the way I you know
earn a living is is through
psychotherapy and a key figure
well there's both the kind of
biographical elements of that is that it
was undergoing my own therapy and planta
in part of the training that made me
realize that you can take your own inner
life seriously and it really does tell
you something and what it tells you you
see if you can grapple with what it
seems to be saying that extends your
participation in life mm-hmm so rather
than you know say being defensive about
life and trying to hold on to your own
conception of things which you know can
come about for all sorts of quite good
reasons nonetheless it restricts and
limits life and whereas understanding
your defenses and more positively
understanding that your your fantasies
and can connect with reality and the
juxtaposition of figures that I quite
like here I find helpful is between
Freud on the one hand and Donald
Winnicott on the other yeah it was a
very significant british psychotherapy
it's very important and he is a romantic
figure but in that romance doesn't come
of age sense and because what Winnicott
said unlike freud is that our inner life
can't just be the sublimation of our
inner fears kind of on to the sky say in
the case of religion and to try and
contain the anxiety we have about
paternal figures or maternal figures or
whatever it might be you know try to
reach some accommodation with these
things that we fear because Winnicott
said we'd all be mad if that was so and
whilst we can be mad some of the time
we're not mad all of the time and he
thought that must mean that our
fantasies actually connect with wider
reality so that we have a sense of
feeling grounded feeling up home feeling
that we've really learned something and
I haven't just conjured another fantasy
out of thin air and I think that so that
sense of how the projections out
actually can inspire back none it's
really important
for understanding how we can be creative
how the imagination can really you know
create works of art that last that that
seemed to give us more life that give us
energy all this kind of side of it as
well and I think you've got that in
Plato too because just to pick up a
little bit on how that connects back
with ancient Greek philosophy I mean I
think what are things which Barfield
showed me actually but it's really
important in Plato actually to realize
that he didn't even have words like
analysis you know that was that's an
Aristotelian neologism and and words
like theory for Plato mean a kind of
journey that you go on the OREA but that
completely changes your perception of
things it is a participative yeah I'm
just think it's not like a vague idea
you have in your head that you somehow
put to the empirical test and so you
know analogy is really important in
Plato and what he tries to do is use
reason to sort of test you know your
kind of immediate ideas to the breaking
point to the a Poirier and then hold
that moment and maybe you do another one
and you sort of test that's the break
its own in one dialogue you might have
you know a whole bunch of ideas that the
test and it's the gaps it's the crack
that lets the lighting yeah and this
felt very similar to me you know in in
modern psychotherapy in fact really the
reason one of the reasons why I became
psychotherapists rather than say an
academic philosopher was I realized that
the work on yourself was as important in
ancient philosophy you know that's a
resonate you've gotta be able to
participate with the heads around you
and it seems to me this early
anglo-american analytic philosophy
really had no conception of that at all
it had what you might call physics Envy
yes just the throwing one nice little
biographical element there as well I did
this physics degree and my physics tutor
he worked on dark dark energy and when I
was doing my physics almost 30 years ago
he had a poster outside his wall outside
his office saying dark energy doesn't
exist and I go and see him every so
often now cuz they be softer now right
so I mean journalistically about physics
or cosmology and he still has that
poster there you know so he - who knows
that physics Envy
doesn't really even exist and and that
was another lesson I learned from him so
yeah this sense of you know with analogy
openness reason sort of testing you need
to have I mean I like the metaphor the
Vic and Stein used to to move into the
unknown you have to have the firm walls
of the well to lower yourself down in
and so you need something you know to go
on and reason does provide that and
other things too but it's got to
constantly I think have this open this
within it and that is where the
participation happens right because
that's when you feel the connection and
it you know works both thank you
therapeutically and I think works
culturally what so that's great there's
a couple things then I want to pick up
on now there's so much what you just
said but hopefully we'll get I like this
the you sort of did this when you
brought in Plato and you were also
talking about right resonance and one of
the things that's one of those shifts
that I didn't talk enough about in this
series I'm gonna talk a lot more about
in after Socrates is the shift in Plato
from dialogue to monologue in Aristotle
because part of what you were doing
there and and I think the
psychotherapeutic analogy and I'm gonna
use the word as seriously as you do if
you'll allow me the psychotherapeutic
analogy is very pertinent the idea about
you know things that and this is where I
think how one of the ways in which the
imaginal differs from for korban not
always but one of the ways from just the
imaginary the images that come up and
catch they catch because they afford
this dialogic relationship between us in
the world not only as you said are they
projections outward from us they afford
the universe you know speaking to us now
in in both ways the active sense of
giving us an insight disclosing
something but also calling to us giving
a sense of you know portending a sense
of a more Ness and a demand on us to be
other than what we are you know will cos
famous line you know after looking at
the the the work of art the the I think
was the torso of Apollo idiot you must
change your life right that sense of you
must change your life and so that's for
me that's sort of a touch
how the imaginal differs from the
imaginary the imaginal it you know it it
catches us it in that though suddenly
the world suddenly speaks through and
and and in both senses we get oh I
didn't see that and also oh I'm being
called beyond myself in ways I hadn't
and and that bad for example comes up
I'm doing a lot of work with that Chris
master Pietro and I send stock and
Jordan Hall on dialectic and dial elo
goes well you get where you get into a
conversation with somebody and it starts
to have those features the conversation
takes on a logo so life of its own and
you start getting those insights that
sense of insight and calling not only
from each other
but the conversation of a as a whole
feels like it starts to enter into
dialogue with sort of the depths of
intelligibility the depths of being and
so I think um why I'm talking about that
and to bring it back to Barfield and
bring it back to what you're saying
about sort of art and imagination and
discernment and maybe this will also get
us back into to religion it's part of
what I see right is also a different
attitude towards language that's coming
when you get into that mode that mode
that I'm trying to talk about where you
know to use one of Plato's metaphors it
goes back to Heraclitus what it take
when it catches fire right and you've
got that um and what I see in is a lot
of a lot of the prophets are talking
about images and that's important until
it does and you know obviously Young
does for man but I see what's more
specific about Barfield and also this
puts him into an important dialogue with
Heidegger and diffusor brings that out
is this turn towards language but not
but but a turn about a turn and yet
we're trying to get a fundamental
reorientation about how we participate
in language and how we understand
language and and part of the few CEA's
argument is in fact he thinks that
Barfield does a better job at that
return to language then Heidegger does
and well and I noticed you you've got
sort of similar aspects run
to your work I wonder if you could speak
to that um you know that this general
theme of if you'll allow me this a way
of putting it because you use the term
as well in your book and it also has
Christian resonance recovering the logos
remember Heraclitus famously said don't
listen to me but listen to the logos
right in my words and what does that
list
what is the logos in language and what
is it to listen to the logos is that a
fan of question do you think yeah well
let me say somethings about it I mean I
think one of the reasons why I think
baffled may do a better job in Heidegger
and say that nervously cuz you know
Heidegger it's a big figure but is I
think that he doesn't have a high kick
hiding its hatred of Plato yes and I
mean the I think Plato understood
reciprocal participation yeah in a way
that comes out of the pre-socratics and
comes out of Heraclitus and the
Heidegger felt the need to reject for
one reason and another I think I think
it's actually that much just the the
state of academic philosophy at the time
actually but anyway that's perhaps that
can I interrupt for just one point
because there's a I've just in the midst
of reading a really good book by rock
Kowski called Heidegger's Platonism
where he makes the argument that the
Heidegger who's lecturing on the cave
analogy in the 30s has a really positive
attitude towards Plato and seems to get
what we're talking about here the
reciprocal opening and things like that
and it's only and but then there's a
shift that comes out later and when he
writes to the you know that the thing on
Plato and the essence of truth where as
you say he makes Plato the villain and
and so there seems to be you know
there's a there's to be an original deep
appreciation and Heidegger of Plato and
then there's a rejection and wachowski
actually argues that if Heidegger had
stayed true to what that original he
might not have made his serious his most
serious mistake which was getting
involved with the Nazis so I just wanted
to put that out there as a potential
resource for people to consider but I
think your overall point is right that
Heidegger right turns on Plato in an
important way
please mark well I think dad about that
because it's you know I feel the spirit
of Plato alive and I get upset actually
when people just go for him but anyway
yet but the words what sort of words
point picking up that and what Barfield
says about that is well actually I mean
I think in other words when I go so
deeper Barford is that words were his
material yeah you know he was a
philologist he realized that if words
enlightened our consciousness now as
they do particularly in poetry and by
that he meant that the poet's task in a
way is to put words together that he
familiarizes them but so is that it
releases the energy or the in the
meaning the felt sense
yeah Alchemist of the word I'm in a
fresh way I mean revivify his words so
prose can be quite poetic but the poet
just goes for that complete her so he
thought that words have a kind of soul
or which just means a vitality and inner
life and that words come from somewhere
you know they speak us as much as we
speak then we co-create with words and
so again this takes him to the kind of
inner life of the worlds the cosmos but
with this balance that we're supposed to
do something with them you know so that
sense of reciprocal participation and
you know this then takes them but this
is where he gets his story from about
the rise and fall of the ways of human
consciousness that if words now carry
something about inner vitality then if
we can track back the way were to change
meaning then they can become what he
called fossils of consciousness and we
can understand how things have changed
and so can also use them to tell a story
of now as well as just try and
experience now yeah so I forget where we
started on that but that's something
about the Offit of words and why there
was so central they were both his
evidence if you like he didn't just sort
of imagine this he didn't just receive
it as if he was mystic and this was
actually quite common in the 19th
century to realize that there is a story
can tell about the developments of words
so I was very struck the
figures as diverse as Jeremy Bentham and
Ralph Waldo Emerson are both realized
that words change meaning in ways that
you can actually track and they tell you
something about the shift of
consciousness and particularly about the
sense of how you know human inner life
and inner life in the world around once
felt quite connected and that's perhaps
where language comes from and then it
goes through these periods of feeling
disconnected which is expressed in the
changing change meanings of words as
well so that way that was very good Mike
I like that
just to bring it back to the original
thread the original thread was a
comparison of a Barfield and Heidegger
on this return to language and that you
know you know Heidegger has this notion
that languages the house over the
shepherd of being kind of thing and yet
defeats here seems to argue that
Heidegger is attitude towards it and
maybe it's kind of like the criticism
you're making of Woodsworth
it's very much the glass indict it's the
letting be and it's letting go but he
thinks that that is I don't want to get
too technical here but the idea is you
know and you talk about this in the book
your book too you know the subject has
become sort of determinate of
objectivity it's a very Cartesian model
it's it's very much about the will to
power an imposition
and then Heidegger is trying to break
out of that but what he does is he just
sort of company Australia he tries to
get the individual as willis as possible
the lassen height um and that that to me
strikes that's kind of ironic because
the terms like Heidegger's still bound
to the very grammar
he's just negating it and that's that's
ironic because that's the criticism he
made of Nietzsche that Nietzsche doesn't
really escape Ando theology he merely
inverts it and the fusee argues that
Barfield goes beyond Heidegger and that
he doesn't get through the process of
glass in height so if we're gonna use a
cart there's not only glass in height
there's dirt Brooke there's breakthrough
right and it's like you said there isn't
just this there's also the calling forth
and the drawing for and so if you see
argue
that Barfield sort of brings back the
the participatory creativity within
logos that's missing from Heidegger and
and and so he Barfield has this notion
that you'll allow me one of my
neologisms that's much more trans
ejected about about this that when we're
using language and you I think you said
it earlier you know it it's being Co
determined its Co creative and it's not
just us letting go and letting be but
it's also dirt Brooke breaking through
that's kind of the core of the
difference at least that as diffuse'
argues what do you think about that do
you think it's a fair reading of
Barfield yeah no I mean it reminds me
two things that Barfield discusses one
is what it takes to make a new word a
new word that really really lasts isn't
just a sort of technical term the
captures something for a small group of
people but and of course any people like
Plato and Aristotle are great coin is of
new words yeah the you know that now we
just assume yeah ah consciousness yeah
yeah yeah and and but he says you know
that that's a struggle that's an effort
and and that is you know as it were
bringing down into language something
that enables you to see it and to focus
on it but then provides the life of the
words so that's one one excellent part
sorry that's excellent
that's excellent thank you for that
that's a very good that's a very good
exemplification thank you sorry please
continue yeah yeah and then the other
thing another another take on it which I
really like and there's really come
alive for me actually is author doesn't
talk a lot about Dante but um I Dante
has been important part of my
psychotherapy story actually you know I
think so I could hope you can very good
it take you into the inferno but it's
not quite sure how to get you up through
purgatory and and Dante's helped me do
that and I think one of things that
Dante realized is that what really takes
you into paradise how
you understand that is when your will
your sight your desire your knowledge
and your awareness chimes more and more
and more with you know he would call it
the divine and site design knowledge
awareness and so on but you can call it
the logos as well and but it's done
freely it's done because you've worked
on yourself and you can sense that
there's no greater enjoyment of the will
desire sight knowledge and so on then
when it chimes with the cosmos what's
also interesting in Dante is that when
he gets into paradise warnings that
rather shocks him at first is that he
still sees lots of individual souls in
paradise he doesn't just sort of see a
kind of divine much and it takes in
quite a lot of time through the paradise
to really appreciate that it's a
diversity in unity and you know it's
kind of harmony I mean which resonates a
lot with what people say about non dual
perception and soul and I think that's
another really important notion that I I
remember when you're talking about how
the will in Heidegger that it's actually
an intensification of will in Dante but
with this alignment as well yeah with
the greater will and what you know what
greater flourishing of the world could
the beers are worth and to be aligned
with the divine will so it's yes there's
something about that going on as well
which I found very that sort of the way
that Dante actually sees these things
it feels very fruitful for me okay so
that brings up something that's
excellent
all right before I forget guys everyone
mark has a video series where he's
taking people through Dante so please
check it out just a little plug for you
there Marcus you're doing done thank you
very much well I really hope I do
believe that you know Dan says many
things but if it's not read as a kind of
spirity transformative text the key
thing even I would say is being missed
so I've been trying to do that so that
brings up something that I think will
deepen the the critical comparison
because when we're talking about this
way we're right we're talking about the
Dante right and of course we're invoking
an idea here we're getting this sense of
you know a will a willing and a
willingness it's both a willing and a
willingness that is sensing as you're
sitting this affinity this affinity and
conformity with the divine and the
sacred and so right and the way in which
we normally understand that voluntarily
binding ourselves to something that we
sense an affinity to right is love right
and you know and love is that love is
how we in the end of the work of and on
another that's how we experience
reciprocal opening and what I see and
what you're saying and you know one way
of understanding Christianity especially
in the figure of Christ is the deep
integration of logos and love together
and that's I think that's a theme in
Dante too but we can explore that
another time what I'm saying is that
sense of logos and love together which
makes me think of we need a conversation
about how that integration goes together
with the reason imagination integration
there's they speak to each other in some
way but that that is also missing and
Heidegger love like that which is a deep
because you see that deep integration
between logos and love of course
exemplified you know in Plato I mean
that the two are inseparably bound
together and of course our culture and
in both Enlightenment and forms of
romanticism are responsible for this
divorce too right yeah yeah well I think
I mean just leap in their babies logos
and arrows
you know arrows I think but if you've
been added together they make philia
they make free yeah I'm the point about
friendship as a kind of love is that
you want your friends to be both fully
themselves while you're fully your so
exactly exactly yeah and that's that's
when you have your conversations with
people and see the other thing I think
right yes and then and then there's a
sense also you get a sense of calling at
times and and in and and and then you
see this more you don't see this at
least clearly in Plato but you you catch
it in Augustine very much that the file
Lia can
I don't know what they can deduce you it
can draw you towards agape it can is
there the there you wanting to matter to
something beyond yourself
took you know and it's right it's it so
it's completely Rhys entering so you
know there's egocentric and then there's
sort of you know polar centric info Leah
and then there's Anto centric in in
agape and what's interesting also is
that turn because what's what I what I
hear bar fields notion of creativity as
distinct from just our notions of making
or sort of decadent romantic notions of
pure self-expression right the notion of
creativity can I don't know can conduce
us into agape by making us aware of the
creativity of God is that a fair thing
to say is that is that fair yeah no I
think that the notion of the Incarnation
the Christian notion there is precisely
that the and the the deepest meaning of
the Incarnation is not something to
happen 2,000 years ago that was just
what made us aware of something that's
happening in every creative moment which
is that the divine is coming into human
form into the material world and it's
creative that's how you know that it's
happens you know so for example I think
music is a very example of this the
music is this strange thing that it's
kind of in between worlds that it is a
physical thing I'm its acoustic but if
you just successful music by security
properties you gap so you know where
that's run but their question is then
where does what on USS music by can it
come from
yeah and there would be a sort of more a
narrower romantic view that would say
for example it's the power of expression
and so on but that doesn't really feel
to take you very far and it doesn't
again have this sense that you know when
you've listened to Mozart or also barks
a particularly you know the your
experience of life has greatly grown
it's long as your
expression but something's been given to
you yeah yeah and you know Barfield
thought that that's because the music
both does something on the horizontal
but also transpose is something on the
vertical as well and that's why it
exists in the imaginal zone in an
intermediate zone very much very much
yeah so it is that I'm not quite sure
why fully on sir what you were saying
there no no let me try and feed it back
to you through what you said what what
I'm trying to suggest is when in a big
of Winnicott here also the transitional
object and serious play but when I'm
involved in serious playing of and with
music right and especially like if I'm
doing something like jazz where I'm
actually not just listening but feeding
back in creativity right that when I
went there's a notion of creativity
there that transcends the making or
transcends the expressive notions of
creativity and gives us a sense of right
it's and we could we can only
participate okay I'll try I'll try a
bold hypothesis and then you can you can
criticize it if you want we only can
participate in the creativity that is
God God's a gapek love when we can get
to that kind of creativity to some
degree in ourselves well or actually
between us and the world and music is
something like that I think that's why
music is so prevalent when people are
trying to get their most you know
pertinent representations or symbols of
the experience of sacredness they often
resort to music and musical analogies
it's pervasive through Taoism as you
probably know I'm a Tai Chi Chuan player
and notice the word by the way I'm a Tai
Chi Chuan Claire alright that's that
that's the Chinese right and so like let
me give you an analogy from that
tradition then I'll give it back to you
and see if I'm if we are getting in sync
you don't really understand the Dao
until you play Tai Chi and then you get
that musical sense of you're
participating in a kind of creativity as
you say it's not a creativity even of a
work of art it's a creativity of a way
of being and that discloses to you
in a participatory fashion the
creativity of ways of being that is the
DAO that's what I'm trying to say does
that is that resonating with you is that
landing for you yeah I mean for sure and
music analogy works for me because I
play the piano there you go and I
remember when I first started having
jazz improvisation lessons for example
and I thought that I was going to be
given this somehow this kind of magic
that I'd suddenly just be able to start
playing jazz and then I spent the next
five years basically doing scales and
and and and and that the point of that
is that all that work is required yes
your participation in this whole musical
cosmos is required before maybe you know
something else can start to kind of this
all will flow for your fingers right now
I've never actually I'm not very good at
jazz at all really I'm not but they did
what it did help me experience on
occasion is sheet music
every so often you realize that the
music is kind of playing you brains
rather than you trying to play the music
and you know so the DAO playing with the
hours I wonder whether there's there's a
similar kind of experience so what I'm
trying to get is that's what you just
did that to me it's conducive or
affording of the flip to agape the flip
from being egocentric to being entre
centric you belong to the music rather
than the music belongs to you but it's
not a passive belonging it's not like
you're just right right that's that's
what I'm trying to get at and that's
what I see if III don't know Markel as
DP as you do but I see when he's trying
to talk about poesis that's what I'm
here he's trying to if you'll allow me
now to really pack into this word he's
trying to say see police' says playing
with language in a way that affords that
flick that's how I'm seeing what
Barfield is doing yeah so I mean that
prior thought and natsu backing get a
bit more Barfield to sort of to resonate
with that I mean one one thought which
is a key thing is that it's actually the
particular that is universe or not the
general yeah
so it's when somebody becomes more and
more and more itself that it becomes
universal not because it kind of becomes
general and you know certainly won the
battles criticisms of say look would be
that they tried to separate subject from
object try to say that what was most
abstract was most true whereas you know
Barfield would say no actually it's it's
the least alive and it has its kind of
uses and particularly if you want to do
things like make machines and that you
don't really need to be alive
although the risk is that you forget
about your own vitality if life gets too
you know taken up with machines but yeah
so there's something about that how it's
very much the the particular that makes
for that access is the universal not the
general right which you would criticize
and so making is artistic rather than
machine like that that's why I was
trying to get to Rand so poesis you know
is it can mean you know making like the
pot has a pope the potter has a poetess
in ancient greek but there's a meaning
why it's kind of got become poetry now
is that this was seen as a sharing in
the kind of materiality you might say of
what you might make a potter household
to to make something human out of the
material and again i mean i got this
from
i think this is an another figure that's
becoming more and more important for me
actually is William Blake and yeah I
think that Blake understood a lot of
this you know he he has kind of
different levels of engagement with the
world which he uses he has names for it
which I do syncretic to him but
essentially what he's doing is saying
you know you can move from a sort of
abstract dead you know reason in the
more logical coherent kind of way
through what he called generation which
is a bit more like the kind of the
processes of nature and are very thick
guns but aren't very conscious through
to a level which is much more about
so you kind of seek the beloved and a
nature becomes a more of an eyes our
relationship with others as well and
then you know the highest level for him
is what he called Eden which is actually
the creative level where you've you know
joined in the whole dance of creation if
you like
you'll make you're as much a maker as a
as an enjoyer as a delight er and that's
good
so I resonate with that quite deeply so
the first thing you said was really
important and there's I mean you get
that for me I get this much more clearly
presented in in some Buddhist philosophy
the idea of you know the inexhaustible
Ness the more Ness that I talked about
the inexhaustible missed that Schlegel
talks about and Schlegel had a huge
influence on Coleridge who had a huge
influence on Barfield so and the future
actually talks about that a lot at the
integral but that that more Ness comes
into what the Buddhists call the section
Asst the section of this is exactly what
you're talking about right that part of
it that I can only I can only come to
know through having an either
relationship with it but that I have a
relationship with it doesn't make it
sort of doesn't enclose it in the
finitude it actually makes it you know
open to the more nests and yet you know
this is Blakes to see the world in a
grain of sand and heaven in a wild
flower kind of idea which i think is
very resonant but the thing that that
then I get when I'm hearing that okay
and then this is this has to do again
with dialectic is all the stuff you know
from the Neil Neil Neil platonic
tradition because you have that sense
you know pearl talks about it and a lot
of his work about this deep
correspondence between levels of
consciousness and levels of being and
how they mutually afford and disclose
each other and that there are there's
askesis there's spiritual disciplines
that can afford us both realizing the
ascension to the one but also realizing
you know the emanation to to all of all
of reality and what's what's interesting
to me about that is the notion of
dialectic gets gets really deepened in
the neoplatonist
something as you said horizontally
between us but also vertically you know
between the levels the ontological
levels and and you see that very clearly
in the workbook what kind of that those
two senses are bound together and one of
the things I've been trying to
articulate with the help of a lot of
people both in text and in person is
trying to get back that sense of
dialectic and this attitude this
existential mode of the Ilocos relating
to the logos precisely mark because I
think it's really needed right now yeah
well for two reasons let me just briefly
say and then I'll let you respond one of
course is just a general point about the
meaning crisis and that's sort of a
critical in the ancient sense of the
word crisis you know mode of judgment
thing but also increasingly because in
response to the meeting crisis there are
all these movements of authentic dial
discourse circling practices and you
know and I'm doing a lot of participant
observation in them and there's a lot
and one of the things and I mean I mean
I mean I mean discourse is one of the
originators of this guy sense sake he's
very open to this point what I see
missing from a lot of these authentic
things is philosophy uh that cultivation
of wisdom and I use that term just as a
way of distinguishing from just academic
philosophy philosophy a-- which i think
is inseparably bound up with this deep
appreciation in the multiple senses of
the word appreciation of logos that they
there's an implicit sense of it in these
practices but it hasn't been explicate
'add and that explication has not wet it
wetted it to philosophy a-- enough and
that's why I think getting this kind of
stuff out is really crucially important
especially right now especially right
now when people are more and more
turning to dialogue and discourse to try
and find out what really matters to them
ya know I think I feel that very
powerfully too and I mean what kind of
me when are you talking there was how
there's a kind of therapeutic approach
for lots of these practices you know
obviously meditation and others that can
be very useful
it can help people feel a lot calmer in
life and even has the kind of insight
capacity where people can understand
their inner lives more subtly but I
think also you do need some metaphysics
in there
yeah because otherwise you get very good
understand your own inner life but it
doesn't really take you anywhere else
and that ultimately is dissatisfying
and that what the reason the metaphysics
can help you do is discern both the
richness of a particular tradition and
that is as much about learning and so on
as it is about the practice and it helps
you discern and grow your practice too
as a result and but at the end of the
day also helps you see how the tradition
itself is just a channel and is just
kind of symbols that itself transmits
something more than just yeah yeah so I
think that that's what learning and and
the metaphysical side can can give you I
actually got this that I was just trying
to remember it and book on I am Blucas
so I found actually really yeah Theo G
in the soul yes yeah yeah it's a great
book I love the way that the awesome I
forget which is bad anyway he breaks
down and these different levels and
talks about how you know say them
because understood that the material
ever of reality has its own way of
refracting reflect doing divine reality
and that at certain times engaging with
material realities absolutely crucial to
open yourself up to that level and then
there's the intermediate levels which is
more you know like say more like reason
but reason in the sense of trying to
kind of bring something into minds to
engage the local capture and so you can
feel the resonance with it and then
there's the kind of no exit level which
moves beyond a reason and is say more
ecstatic or something like that you
might have really communication and
cosinus
yeah yeah I love that how this the
integration of all those three level
understand is in is it in iron because
and I've tried to work this out in my
own therapy practice actually healing in
the sense of you know being more open to
not just what's going on for the
individual and their only life which you
have to do all that work because
otherwise people never you know realize
that their own inner life is not the
whole cosmos but the minute people can
begin to kind of step back from a bit a
bit to bring in something else that
takes people into these wider and it
often happens quite naturally because
people have I don't know they have
synchronistic experiences or their
dreams seem to be not just about
themselves or they get interested in
Alan Watts videos or something like that
you know and then and then you can kind
of help that expansion to that's
wonderful I thought oh yeah a picture
it's sure a theory that's why I did it
yeah that's a great book and a lot of
what he writes is really interesting
yeah so I am Blucas and then later
Provost differ from Platonists in that
they both - Tom the material world is
sort of ultimately close to prime matter
which he plated with evil I am Lucas and
Brooke lists are much more positively
disposed towards the natural world
although I think I'm because I
understood that the evil ultimately for
all that it can be foul it's a falling
away from being yeah so the material
world doesn't fall away from being it
definitely is that's well certainly
that's very well
and then the interesting thing about I
am blackest onward is in addition to
theoria right which is the contemplative
practices you bring in theory Jia which
are these ritual practices and and so
you know there's a there's a weaving
together of philosophy and religion that
until recently was really looked down
upon in academic scholarship but within
the laughs especially because of the
work of people like Shaw we've now come
back and appreciate wait wait wait we're
doing a lot of this like we do you often
people you know thanks to the work of LA
Paul and I in this color I talk about
this in my series you know going through
these transformative experiences these
are not things you can sort of reason
your way through you need these symbolic
you need Winnicott you need these
transitional zones and objects right it
and you have to play with the
seriously and so you know they're there
there is a deeply important role in
aspiring to become other than what we
are for you know this kind of serious
play this is serious symbolic play so I
just the notion of ritual I feel is
increasingly important actually and yeah
and again it's Plato you know one of the
things which I never really understood
when I study my PhD was why I know
people always disappearing off to
perform rites in platonic dialogue or
Plato then ends the dialogue with a
whole myth as if yet somehow the kind of
grand finale and I think yeah I think is
the whole point actually you need these
multiple levels of engagement yes be
able to participate in what's being sort
of discussed and revealed yes and and
other like rituals because they do have
this open quality that they are there
situating you to receive something as
much as anything else I mean again
magical or robotic of course too but
when done with the right intention you
know about is a very expansive kind of
gesture I agree and one of the
interesting points that Agnes callow it
makes if you accept all the arguments so
I'm not going to review them here
because I've done them extensively that
you can't sort of infer your way through
becoming some okay like she is it let's
use whatever his example because it's
pertinent she says you want it you want
to come to like classical music and you
don't currently like it and you want
you're not doing this because you want
to date women or you want to actually
come to light classical music for its
own sake and so you take a music
appreciation class and she gives all
kinds of arguments about like why you
can't reason your way into that because
you don't have that value you don't have
those preferences you don't have that
perspective of knowing you don't have
that identity so you write and you don't
know you know you don't know what you're
gonna gain and you don't know what
you're gonna lose right and so you can't
use any sort of standard decision matrix
inferential processes and what you have
to basically do I argue is you have to
go you you you train you do this you
basically afford appreciation through
sort of ritual behavior where you you
you get into this liminal zone where you
play between worlds until you get a
taste and you
right but what to bring that back if we
accept that core argument and I make it
more rigorously elsewhere right about
the role of let's call it ritual in
aspiration by which we come to
appreciate again both senses of the word
or actually all three senses evaluation
understanding and liking right right she
says look and she doesn't quite make
this explicit but it's definitely at the
core for argument we aspire to being
rational we aspire to being rational and
it could be I'm I'm not as rational as I
should be or could be and I aspire to
that and but that is also and she said
and here's that here's the crucial thing
if we if that aspirational process -
rationality is not itself an inferential
process but if we say it's not part of
rationality we fall into a performative
self contradiction because we couldn't
recommend it anybody become more
rational because we would be
recommending to them a fundamentally
irrational process so we have to this
identity calls it proleptic rationality
and the reason why I'm bringing that up
is you know that again these things that
we've tended to push aside you can see
now there's for modern work is now
coming no no no you know ritual and
rationality are deeply interpenetrating
in a way in which because you know
ritual was one of the hobgoblins of the
Enlightenment philosopher a ritual
behavior was the meaningless useless
magical behavior but it turns out that
it's actually integral in fact like like
to your very conception of rationality
you can't separate the two out in any
clean fashion yeah yeah again a couple
of thoughts the the Buffett was
certainly very aware of one was the the
way that the medieval world understood
the sort of the grammar of a sense if
you like you know begins with the
literal goes through the allegorical
which is sort of the moral level kind of
tells you a bit about how to live
there's the crucial topological moment
which is where you're in that state of
not-knowing
struggle but you feel something is
changing yeah till he gets the an ego
kick
and a new level I'm an ultimately the
divine level and I think about fielding
word their tree and I'm wondering about
this so I'm not sure it's quite right
but what you were just saying there was
actually the word intuition
yeah and I'm Barfield actually from
Rudolf Steiner which is a whole other
side to him yeah which we do and don't
understand but but certainly one things
which I think he did bring into his idea
of the imagination is that imagination
goes through these three three there's
the first of those the imagination which
is mixed up with fantasy and projection
and so on it's discerned and becomes
inspiration because you get a sense of
what you're receiving and but when that
inspiration is fully sort of becomes
part of your consciousness becomes
rational in that big more expansive
sense and it becomes an intuition that
you're then able to live your life from
so it becomes part of reality yes I
think that there's something about that
seems to connect with what you were
saying there a bit it does it doesn't it
circles back around to this different
attitude towards language again that we
were talking about earlier because one
of the places where that comes out for
me as I do a practice called Lexi Oh
Davina the divine reading and you're
trying to do exactly that you try to you
get sort of your initial associations so
first of all what you do is you don't
just read the text you recite it and
what that means is try to pick up on the
imaginal try to pick up on the metaphors
and try to try to at least imagine what
it would be like to enact the metaphor
right and then you let the associations
come up and then you try to like you say
you try to discern between what's just
sort of projected fantasy and then what
seems to be you'll allow me and the pun
is intended will you get an inkling of
well you get an inkling of beyond all of
that and then the degree to which that
starts to call you out and that's what
you're trying to do it as you move
through those levels of how you're
reading the text it sounds very similar
to what you're saying about how you're
sort of educating imagination in a
powerful way and it's interesting
because you get this different feel for
language you get this very different
feel for language and it was poetry the
awoke Barfield to that here's why when
he first met CS Lewis and became one of
the Inklings he he he was very depressed
in his early 20s he felt very much
demeaning crisis
said that you know my life felt like an
ingrown toenail that I was wearing my
body like it was ill shape and clothes
you know all these kind of ways he tried
to describe it which are very vivid and
two things happened long as he fell in
love so the eros tension inside him woke
up and but also he realized that he
could read poetry but follow the energy
of the words and resist just immediately
kind of collapsing interpreting you know
sort of trying to pin the poem down
what's it really saying that kind of
thing and the point about that I think
is if you do that too soon you just stay
in your gerund yet will give you if you
stay in your current consciousness you
need to hold open up all possibility of
something so when you say the next
Davina I think it's very much like that
and it's trying to sort of and it can be
very painful and I think one of the
reasons why death and dying is such a
central feature of these great wisdom
traditions is that it can be really
distressing at times and it's like it
okay knows that and you know the a
Poirier in plate so you know basically
led to Socrates's death because it is
too many people play as we recon says
yeah yeah that's really yeah okay well
this mark for fault I think we're sort
of we came to a place where we could
serve come to an end I try not to get
let these get too long or they become
people won't watch them kind of thing
first of all I thoroughly enjoyed that
and I would like to extend an invitation
for you to come back and you and I have
another dialogue you know sometime
within the next month perhaps if you
carry this on because I for me I really
enjoyed this and I felt there was a
tremendous amount of resonance between
us and then for me too because it feels
integrating for me actually with the
work that you're doing that I have I
confess I slightly have the
psychotherapists prejudice about
cognitive science right but I think you
know I very much being this thing's what
you're saying about the new expansion of
cognitive science and I thought for
anything else I I'm very hopeful that
bringing together of these particular
disciplines which
the benefit of psychotherapy because
psychotherapist or his own problems
happen those as well
so yeah I think that apart from anything
else you know that's really nice to
share thank you um you might want to
take a look at the discussion I have
I've got another one coming out with
Greg on reeks
he's a psychotherapist in the United
States and he's also been in sort of
dialogue with my work in this emerging
for EE Kansai picking up on some of the
spirituality so you might find that
interesting anyway Mark III I'd like at
the end of this to give people sort of a
I don't want to just end I want to give
you like if there's anything that you
know feel you need to front you want to
still give voice to any summative or a
thing you want to say please take this
opportunity now to do so anything also
you want a point you know my viewers to
in your own work feel free to plug make
a plug right now thank you yeah well I
mean this is this is definitely an
ongoing you know life project for me
it's not something that I've sort of
come to the end of and that's part of
its excitement I think that a real the
cutting out for me more more and I hope
this might come out for me as I I'm just
about to start the purgatory with the
Dante youtubes and then you know we're
go on to the Paradise later this year I
guess it's a bit like you know your many
parts so the meaning crisis yeah I got
to the end of the inferno just before
Easter and I felt quite relieved at
least I'd done something you know but
yeah but it's it's I think the Vanguard
for me is how this connects with you
know what people might only call BAM
were a very directly involved with which
is normally called the esoteric
traditions it's a difficult word because
it means we're sort of spooky and
mystical not just kind of implicit and
hidden I think there's something really
crucial in all on the one hand the
experiences that people have and which
might be called the supernatural the
paranormal whatever I'm very influenced
by another psychologists of religion
called Jeffrey cried bell on this who
thinks that the reason why people have
all these
experiences is that we've lost the
capacity to discern them actually so as
it were these vitality Zoar this
intelligence these agencies kind of
impress upon us
particularly when were in fragile
moments we're not ego strength tends to
fall apart and how we discern that I
think is there's something really
important in that for me it's much more
array packs and we'd be talking about so
far but you know I think these things
happen and we've got to try and
understand that and so that's on the one
hand and then the other hand is what
this means for religion actually you
know I sort of Christianity is kind of
my tradition and it's one that you know
I feel fairly fluent in I've got a lot
from Buddhism as well but you in terms
of practices and and what this means for
a religious worldview because I sort of
feel that the way out of the meaning
crisis is going to look something like
the religious imagination and the reason
why I feel that is that I feel it ends
there we can't bootstrap our own way out
of it we are called in so I think into
relationship with nature with the cosmos
and with the divine I think ultimately
and so staying open to how that might be
the case and by open I don't just mean
you know not being too skeptical but
trying to discern the inward flow of
divine energy you know in the small
wayside we've got gold finches nesting
in our garden this spring and during
this lockdown phase they are like little
angels expression you know they feel
like little centers of energy but a
calling for something in me as much as
doing their own thing and so I you know
trying to be open to that inferiority is
yeah it's kind of where it feels at the
vanguard for me I'm not completely sure
what to make of it I just feel I got to
make something of it well thank you very
much mark thank you very much and like I
said I hope that you'll come back again
on voices with reveille keen we can have
another discussion perhaps of some of
these themes that you've now just
introduced at the end oh thank you very
much appreciate all you're doing as well
thank you very much
okay take good care